So in this particular recording, we're talking about the number one point release, the skinny leg, so number two point release, skinny leg, and then we'll go into the price pause as well.
So generally what happens is, you know, here, liquidity is drying out. One side of the range is susceptible. This may be picking up, or this may be feeding a high time frame level here.
Price is already extended down as far, et cetera. And then, you know, liquidity dries out.
inside of this range and you have a relative surge on one side.
So a big order comes into play.
Or it could be an event driven, like an interest rate decision,
a surprise rate decision, which will see more profound,
bigger, faster reactions, okay?
Now, in normal market conditions,
you can still get very generally slower,
and then it starts to increase in terms of volatility
because there's some fractal levels left here
and prices just absorbing them,
okay, going deeper and deeper.
into them, but either way, the start of the run, once it gets above the liquidity base and
it picks it up, we generally start to see some trending movement, some faster price action,
some more volatile, but supported price action in one direction of the market.
The reason being inside of this range, there was relative stability, okay, and then you have
a surge that triggers a response from banking algorithms, pricing engines.
and they are forced to push price higher to look for liquidity to fill the new order coming into play here.
Okay, so it dislocates the market, there's a relative surge, it triggers a response,
and those responses can further compound how fast and how far the price wrong goes.
It's important to note at this point of release, there is a psychological and a shift in the state liquidity as well
where a significant profound effect occurs or shift occurs and that again pushes price on one direction
in the market it can be in you know it can be circumstantial and generally it will be circumstantial
by that what i mean is there was just not enough offers and just a small sometimes a small
nudge because of the state of liquidity at that point in time this nudge was relatively bigger
to the amount of offers available and once we got above those offers
there's a bit of a liquidity void and price starts to trend and trend it's dislocated it triggers
the response and that response forms the price one that shift in the state forms and compounds the
price run okay um but generally speaking what we like is when we have when i when i get this skinny
leg if price is coming back through that skinny leg i want to see it slip and extend into the
point of release let's have a look at some examples so this again is
pound usd my favorite chart a very clear example is here liquidity is drying out this is the
core basis visible on the h4 price pumps out of it okay and now on the way back down on the right
the next day or two days the next day actually price actually starts the gap slip right to the
the point of release of this core liquidity base okay same applies with this one but again it's a
bit of a slower price response price leaves it slowly you know on a relative
basis to this and again it draws back early morning or later in the morning sorry
right before afternoon and it gives you a bigger response same applies for the
other side of the market so there's a bit of a base there price responds near
it pauses accumulates accumulates and pushes through it which is absorption
same applies with this response comes into the base
response comes into the base which is ultimately showing us that is not favorable response to the
game okay because there's a relatively efficient price movement into their core base but again
price extended and efficiently out of the core base what is to do it draws right back up to the
clean breaking point okay same with this extended really inefficiently price has no trouble
trending straight through it trending straight through it shelf watch extension bomb by the what i mean is this was the
inventory top was picked price came picked grabbed the last bit at the bottom of the shelf
and extended height okay um same with this you know if price was to extend uh later date
i'm looking for a response there okay i don't think it will but that's the kind of responses
that we look for it's important to know is it's never going to be clean it's never you know
it doesn't have to be clean it should be recognizable because you've seen it so many times
And what you'll come to terms with is although this is a big liquidity base, okay, and although
that it may not always be clean, the fact that we can identify constituent parts and different
features inside of this core base that allows us to refine, okay, we can observe them, we can
actually identify them. It's more objective rather than just saying, oh, I'm going to use
the middle of the level, the bottom of the level. Okay. So again,
this instance core base a fractal base inside this bigger base price pumps
dries out comes right back to the unfilled part even though the the point of
release level gave a response there as well and this leaves liquidity price
picks it up comes back responds off the top side okay now really we're just
going to talk about the price pause so again we're talking about the
shift in the state of liquidity. So this picked up a fractal from January 3rd lows, the spike.
We got past this bit of inventory here, poked past it, which is telling us that sellers are
weak, just like this inventory was picked and it held, held, sellers found no trouble from
buyers there or there, just like this clean breaking point, this fractal held, this core
liquidity base held, price came and picked the bottom, had no trouble and it carried on moving
down when you have an extension like this at the bottom of a price of a
bottom of a price from and when price is picking up a core base on a high
time frame on the left side of price once price is extended enough to the
downside we are starting to expect price to drawback of the extensions right
we're expecting this run to have gone weaker and ultimately price will start to get
past the last bits of inventory of sell side liquidity that should have held for
for sellers to continue pushing lower.
Why is the inventory weaker?
Because the further price travels,
the less, the smaller the bulk of liquidity
pushing on the side of the market,
the smaller that bulk gets, the weaker the run gets.
So again, we invalidated the shelf,
put in a high, the price comes,
picks up the core base, picks it up again,
the low is holding a very, very specific parameter
for when we're trading a low.
And then naturally, again, the next day it comes,
dries out around this H1 base.
And then once you got above that,
this shelf here in a way,
once you got above that shelf of the inventory,
what you start to see is price responds
of fractal or residual levels,
but they don't materially push back on price.
Because what's happened here is inside here
was the bulk of the liquidity of this whole move down.
The bulk of it was transferred down
because it keeps getting picked up, picked up
there, picked up there, picked up there, picked up there.
And that is transferring and passing on the liquidity
that's pressuring this move down.
Of course, it's also a function of a lack of buyers
at all these levels.
There's some buyers, but just not enough
to get past these core bases.
So that's the characteristic of when price is strong,
the core bases continue to hold.
Once you get above the core base, that again,
of course, when the low is held,
that's showing intent that buyers are stronger
than this core base, and this core base
once you get above the core base there is a profound shift and what we start to
expect is the price pause so when it comes into a residual level for it not to
materially push price back down rather for you know the response that we're
getting really is a function of this inefficient extension this leg was weak
because of the way you extended price draws back to the clean baking breaking
point extensions get filled that is a very clear example of it and then it
carries on building and building and building,
forming another core liquidity base.
Price pumps, the point of release,
there's a skinny leg, and then at a later date,
it came right back, right back to it,
and picked up liquidity and responded.
The same thing happens here.
Liquidity is drying out on this core base,
but because this is picking up a H1 level,
now this has its own liquidity,
the top is picked and it's picked again,
liquidity is dry, and then it goes in a price run.
At a later date or later time, it comes
but picks that level again.
Okay.
Same thing's happening with all these small wicks.
So if you were to zoom in, which you can do,
what we see in here is price.
This is a core base.
Top side was picked right there.
Price came, grab the bottom.
There's a transfer of liquidity.
Now this has some bulk liquidity.
You can see it on the way out.
You can see on the way out.
The top side was picked.
Price came and grabbed the bottom after, you know, you got
this level. And look again, there's a core base there. Price, the bottom was picked,
and price came to the top side, washing this level away, because the top and the middle
and the bottom are picked as well. But what we see here is intent, because the buyer, the low
is holding. There is a very clear example, a very clear parameter that we have for a load
to work. Why is this also working here as well? Why are the bids finding no trouble for
continuing higher? Because when we zoom out and look at the broader price front, when we look at
the broader state of liquidity, what we've had is price pick up lows or buyers, flip
above the shelf, rendering sellers weak, because we got above the inventory where the
sellers were, rendering sellers weak, buyers take control, and of course, buys find no trouble
bidding price up, okay, because these are all residual levels until you reach a non-residual
level. That's why price pumped past this high on Friday. This was picking up a residual level
right here, point of release. Okay, but really and truly this whole,
whole area was a fracked was a liquidity base it just came to the point of release and that
helps us again refine these levels how are you going to become more proficient at finding these
responses and stuff exercising okay you're going to take one aspect of a price run a price feature
put it into context of the price run anyway so train your eyes and spot in these levels
etc spotting these runs seeing the definition in price ultimately you want to become a
specialist in one aspect it could simply be the inefficient extensions
into a level into a core base now to be honest that's the most definitive okay by
that what I mean is it's the most observable the most easily identifiable price
feature and price behavior is the inefficient extensions and legs into a price
into a core liquidity base but the main the real skill starts the real skill is
identifying before the response what kind of response you're going to get is it
going to materially push to new lows? Is it going to just fill in this inefficiency and find
liquidity at the core base, which is feeding price and continue higher? How do we anticipate and
differentiate between what kind of response we're going to get? Using the anatomy of a price
swing. There's your low. There is the shelf flip. Once you are above the shelf, there's a shift
in the state of liquidity. These runs are mid-price run, and we're not expecting huge responses
off them so we would expect this leg to get filled but not for it to materially
pushed to new lows and then we have a baseline expectation for what kind of
response we're expecting and then price starts to deal this level off okay and it
comes back higher we already know that the buy liquidity is now weak it's very
unlikely the buys will continue because it's not fitting the general guideline of
what price should be doing when it forms a price swing when it goes above a shell
When the low is in, if the low doesn't hold, it's not fitting the parameter of a low.
Why should the low hold?
Because first of all, the leg that pushed down towards the bi liquidity is weak.
There's a nice bit of buyers inside this base.
The bias should be stronger than the sellers.
That's why we look for the low to hold.
Every successful load, the low holds.
No?
Just like this low held there.
Just like this low held here.
Just like this fractal low held here.
And it formed the high low on the swing retest of it.
Just like this low on the way out, it didn't even come.
back to pick it up. This low, which ultimately did push, okay, was a successful low, just a small
version of it. Again, the same parameters apply. And the prices of fitting these parameters, you know,
we look to cut those trades, we look to get out of those trades. So a key point here is when you
have a shift in the state of liquidity, any residual level is just going to form a price
pause. It's tradable, especially if this was a daily chart, I would love to go short there
and fill that inefficient extension. 100%. You know, there's no two ways.
about it I would love to take that fucking trade why we observed on the five
minute is just so we can see them happening more frequently rather than waiting
five years for a flipping price run we can see occur on a five minute 50
minute one hour more often and you know the more you observe the more you
engage with these the more you're gonna identify the most probable reactions the
most probable anatomy you know the structures and then you basically know when to
engage when not to engage but again even though price went
back to here look there's a base price response that is a price for okay and then once you got above
this shelf here the inventory of this move down which came to pick up buyers there what does price do
it holds it pauses again it pauses runs price nearly comes there but it definitely responds there
okay why did this response not materially push price back up because by that point we already
put in a high lower high we already invalidated the shelf and this was just mid-price
from level when this is the core base okay response trade will response if that was on the
weekly I take it but you know because of where that core accumulation is where that
price pause is of it tells us what kind of response we can expect now another point I
want to make about price pauses okay is from a trade management perspective so
Let me just find an example.
Okay, cool.
So this is a bit of a price pause and a higher time frame.
Okay, so price extended.
Yeah, price extended, came back down,
found liquidity at this base here, pick the top of it up,
and there's obviously going to be a five minute accumulation
which released out there, picked it up,
and then continue the price run, okay?
What's happening there is, you know,
There's accumulation here, there's buy orders.
It dislocates because an engine trigger is kicked off.
It forms the price run, pressure dries out,
buying pressure dries out,
and it draws back into the core base.
And it builds up liquidity.
There's a lot of inventory here,
the inventory holds, and it continues,
and it does the same thing.
Now, let's just say you took a short here, right?
It's a counter flow.
What you have to contend with in managing this trade,
okay, is the core base that's feeding this price here.
Okay, if you expect to hold this trade for it to go to zero,
okay, you're gonna go from, you know,
there's gonna be some US dollar strength
and pound is gonna just continue rocketing
to the downside over the next five decades
and you're trying to catch a high of the five decades there.
What you have to get past is this inventory.
Okay, and what we're looking at is,
is this inventory, has this inventory got
leftover liquidity, okay, is this a high time frame level, basically, relative to where I'm going
short? Is there enough liquidity inside of this price pause, the shelf as well, that is going to
basically eat my profits? So where price is going to respond there and draw back up? Because
if that's the case, okay, what you need to be doing is thinking about taking some equity at this
level because what happens is if you don't you take the short you already felt heat there but
it fit the parameters of a high and then it comes down you're in like five 10 15 our profit
and then you really start to it comes right back on you again okay and now you're less in profit
and it goes right back on you again and you're less in profit okay and this can cause profound
psychological effects on how you're going to manage your trades in the future okay it can
make you emotional. And this is what you have to kind of identify you. You have to, when you're
in a short, you're going to have to contend with these, with these price pauses, these shelves,
these inventories. Now, the point here is, we can anticipate this being a small response,
okay, depending on if this is picking up a residual level on the left, a mid-price run level.
We wouldn't expect a mid-price run level to materially push price back down in a case like
this okay so then this price pause becomes our take profit then this price pause becomes our
core inventory that needs to hold for buyers to continue pushing on one side of the market so let's
have a look at the one hour if I can find here we are so price responded of some
fractal level there okay even if you're short okay price is going to have to
fuck with this level to get through it.
It's going to have to either sit on it and trade through it
or is literally going to come into it,
has a relatively inefficient move into the core level,
the bottom side of the fractal,
and it continues again.
So depending on what kind of response you're trading here
is going to determine if you are going to either take
equity out inside of the shelf,
or if you're just going to close the trade
and look for price to continue.
okay is it a counterflow are we countering just this skinny leg or is the whole run weak and we're
looking for the shelf to break down and we're going to determine that depending on what level this
is picking up number one and number two um whether the level you know sorry what time frame the
level is that is picking up and number two whether the level is mid price run and this instance
okay it you know it was mid price run okay price ended up coming to the first
feeding fractal that's above price there okay same applies with other other examples as well so
if you're short up here this is the shelf price extends really inefficiently into a core fractal
there and this is a mid price run level but if you are short here price is extended and you're
you're trying to trade directionally you're going to face a lot of
lot of heat when price is drawing right back up and you've gone from 30 y'r back to pretty much
nothing and it might even take your break even stop it okay so you have to then differentiate between
whether if you're catching an absolute high and this instance you're you're definitely
confident that price is going to go to new lows why you know this the bottom was picked
the top the bottom was picked the top was picked and then it ran to new highs that's a shelf
wash extension shelves are relative for the time frame and then this shell
shelf here was on this price run okay just this price run that was the shelf when you
first take a short there first you know you've got to contend with that you want to look at is
price absorbing that level is it moving through it is this level likely to give in what is this
picking up what is what time frame is this shelf present on and then once you got beneath there
and then price starts to become really inefficient personally i'd look for a counter flow in a case like
that rather than try to hold this original short you know for a million pips in profit
because you're so excited about the trade yeah you really have to contend with these
levels the more you engage you're gonna find these parameters you're gonna refine
your parameters as well and your eyes gonna be better at spotting whether you
shouldn't be taking equity out of this trade because remember even if you take the
short you close 50 60% of it that doesn't mean you can't take that short bit
that doesn't mean you can't take that longer there as well because
this was the inventory of this whole price movement down,
the inventory was inside this box.
We invalidated it after picking up a H1 level,
came to the point of release kind of area,
the base top, and went on a price run, okay?
Prime, really and truly,
the only reason I believe price to have extended this far back
is not because of the nature of this level, okay?
It's more to do with the nature of the extension,
how far price run it left it weak this triggered and yielded a bigger response and that bigger
response caused the bigger shift in the state of liquidity at that point in time for this price
run which allowed for a more of a sustained price run on one side of the market and then once
this run was tired came back and picked up liquidity we got beneath this shelf and then again
this whole leg is now washed or tired sorry okay because we've shifted the same
state liquidity. And this is all in the context of the higher time frame. Okay, this is picking
up a fractal level inside here, 15 minute level. Yeah, that's price pauses. You have to
contend with them. Even another example is this. You're short here. You know, I'm looking to go
long in these examples. I'm not looking to hold my short trade for a million Pips
profit because you can take this short and this accumulation here.
okay and maybe as these trades because the shift in the state of liquidity has occurred because you know then
this inventory has been picked up picked up again washed out we're weakening the support for this leg
we're weakening it weakening it then it's very likely that once you get past that shelf price
goes into midflop okay so there's just not enough bids there bids there and those sellers continue
to pressure on one side of the market as a function of a lack of bids
so maybe you know you'll find that the shelf flip trade after price has picked up a good enough level
after the leg that ran to the level is weak enough that is the shell flip trades that you want to
hold okay provided they go into midflow pretty quickly right not going to make this particular
video too long the next we're going to cover is a shelf the shelf bottom shelf top and of course
right now this is a lot of information watch these videos over again over and over
Again, they will all start to make sense the more you engage and you're going to remember key pieces of information on just these small minute details that we're covering here.
And you're going to see even more minute details relative to your engagement, which further substantiates, you know, your understanding these principles of our plans of the market, how you should be trading it, etc.
It's all going to come together basically and form a fucking question.
But other than that, you know, we'll get onto the other parts of a price room.
Thank you.